June 1941
Last family moments.
The Germans have won a series of easy
victories.
Exhilarated by their success in Norway,
the Netherlands, Belgium and France,
they're gearing up for a secret
operation
in the east.
Everyone is convinced they will be home
by Christmas.
How could they have known they were
embarking on a war of unprecedented
violence
which in the space of months would leave
6 million dead?
The actors in this event, both soldiers
and civilians, Germans and Soviets,
would record their experiences
in short amateur films.
The Germans filmed a lot
as well as in letters, journals and
diaries.
Hans Roth, a soldier in an infantry
division, writes in his journal.
>> In a few hours the air will be filled
with the howling and screeching of
shells.
The impacts will tear apart the fields
and the roads.
Farewell my dear wife and my little
Erika.
Farewell my parents.
You'll be in my thoughts tomorrow.
Do not worry.
Soldier's luck will be with me.
>> A 17-year-old tank operator writes,
>> The long-awaited moment
experienced a hundred times in my
imagination
has finally arrived.
Am I afraid?
I'm too inexperienced to be afraid.
Instead,
I feel great excitement.
The same excitement that filled me when
chasing a deer through the woods on a
hunt.
Behind us
our comrades.
Ahead of us
somewhere hiding in the trees, in the
houses, in the bushes
the Russians.
>> Sunday, June the 22nd, 1941.
Under the code name Operation
Barbarossa, Nazi Germany invades the
Soviet Union.
In the first hours of the attack, the
Luftwaffe carpet bombs Soviet aerodromes
all along the border.
The coast is clear for the Panzers.
Hitler clearly designated the enemy a
few weeks prior.
The Communist is not a comrade under any
circumstances.
It is to be a war of annihilation.
If we do not approach it this way,
in 30 years time communism will be
facing us again.
The Germans have violated the
German-Soviet Non-Aggression Treaty
signed 2 years prior.
The Soviets are taken by complete
surprise.
An infantry lieutenant writes,
>> All we have to do is attack.
Forward, forward, and ever forward.
While our artillery blast the Russians
with gunfire, explosives, steel, bombs,
and shells.
Believe me, there's no doubt that 4 to 5
weeks from now we will stick our flag on
the Kremlin, and the swastika will fly
over Moscow.
>> The Soviet Union is a giant with feet of
clay,
predicted Hitler and Franz Halder, the
mastermind behind Operation Barbarossa.
We only have to kick in the front door,
and the whole rotten Soviet edifice will
come tumbling down.
4 million soldiers, including Germany's
Axis allies, launch a three-pronged
attack.
In the south, the forces attack towards
Kiev and the Ukraine. In the center,
towards Moscow.
And in the north, towards Leningrad.
June the 24th,
just 2 days into the offensive, the
Germans have already reached Vilnius,
the Lithuanian capital.
A week later, early July, they take
Riga, the capital of Latvia.
Succeeding beyond their wildest
expectations.
A peal of bells greets the German
troops.
Annexed by the Soviet Union 2 years
earlier, the Baltic states hope to
regain their independence.
Heinrich Harper, an army doctor, is part
of a battalion in the spearhead of the
attack.
In his memoirs, published after the war,
he recounts,
>> A crowd of Lithuanians gathers on the
roadside to watch us go by.
Some villagers throw us cigarettes or
hand us mugs of water and freshly baked
bread.
>> [cheering]
>> Here and there, a green, yellow, and red
flag flaps lazily in the light breeze.
The Lithuanians believe now in a German
victory
and have proudly taken out their
national flag again.
We can see in their eyes that they would
willingly give us their meager
possessions in the hope that the
Russians never return.
>> In western Ukraine, too, the Germans are
greeted by jubilant crowds.
Persecuted by Stalinism, the inhabitants
believe their ordeal will soon be over.
A German sergeant rejoices,
>> In some localities, we even see
triumphal arches,
banners in Russian and German.
The Ukrainian people thank their
liberators,
the courageous German army.
Long live Adolf Hitler.
The people are overjoyed.
In fact, here in Ukraine, we're lucky.
We're not only fighting the poisoners of
the world,
we're liberating an entire nation from
an unbearable yoke at the same time.
And this delights us.
>> A week earlier in Leningrad, the day of
the invasion.
Despite the surprise, news of the German
attack does not cause panic.
The front is far away.
The inhabitants stroll, make the most of
the fine sunny weather.
On the radio, Molotov, the foreign
minister, has reassured the population.
Nikolai Nikulin, 17 years old and still
at high school,
is unaware he's enjoying the last
carefree moments of youth.
In his memoirs, The War Diaries, he
recalls that day.
>> I greeted the war, if not with
indifference, then with some detachment,
like the majority of my compatriots.
We all expected a series of swift
victories from our army, whom our
newspapers repeatedly described as
invincible, the best in the world.
In town, the atmosphere was festive.
Groups of boisterous young soldiers in
new uniforms roamed the busy streets.
On every street corner,
singing, accordion music, and gramophone
tunes filled the air.
Those who had just been called up
hurried to get drunk one last time and
to celebrate the departure for the
front.
>> [music]
>> Until the 11th hour, Stalin refused to
believe Germany would invade.
Precious hours are lost organizing the
mass mobilization of men and resources,
so troops and equipment are hurriedly
sent to the different fronts.
A young soldier, newly called up, is
anxious.
>> I'm writing to you from the train taking
us to the front.
It is strange
and even alarming. The vast majority of
officers seem to have been on holiday.
I can't believe it.
>> A journalist on the front at the time
recalls
>> The day of the attack, many tank units
were still busy changing engines.
Many artillery units had not received
munitions and the Air Force had not been
supplied with fuel.
>> The Red Army actually has plenty of
tanks and munitions, but desperately
lacks personnel capable of using them.
Stalin's drastic purge of 1937 decimated
the Soviet officer corps and now new
officers have to be hastily trained.
Some cannot even read a map.
The majority have served for less than a
year and do not know their men or their
colleagues.
To make matters worse, dedicated
communists have been promoted over
competent leaders.
These officers are experts on Leninist
Marxism,
but have only a basic knowledge of
military tactics.
So, arriving at the front late June are
disheartened by the chaos on the ground.
One writes to his wife,
>> "We desperately lack tanks and aircraft.
We have received three tanks and five
airplanes at the front while the Germans
have countless numbers of both."
>> Another confides,
>> "Our leaders flee, but they order us to
stay and retaliate.
The vast majority of us think we cannot
beat the Germans."
>> Another protests,
>> "I fought two battles,
and it was obvious that our commanders
are incapable of leading.
All they can do is shout slogans."
>> Attack, counterattack, attack again.
The army chief supply Moscow's doctrine,
which prioritizes attack over defense.
Under duress, they send wave upon wave
of infantry into battle against the
panzers automatic weapons and cannons.
Staying on the right side of Stalin is
all that matters,
even if it means a pointless loss of
life and equipment on a massive scale.
Early July, the German doctor Heinrich
Harper and his battalion are already in
the heart of Belarus.
>> Our first prisoners.
We watch them keenly,
eager to get to know the enemy.
There's a platoon of them.
They sport shabby, tan khaki uniforms,
vaguely military jackets,
and closely cropped hair.
Their heavy faces are expressionless.
>> A radio operator infuses.
>> The German army began its conquest of
the East Berlin week ago.
Unbelievable.
We all feel the same irrepressible
desire to forge ahead.
The German army is proving on every
front that it has the best weapons and
soldiers.
>> Nothing can stop Operation Barbarossa.
Barely a week into the offensive, Minsk,
the Belorussian capital, is within
artillery range.
700,000 soldiers are engaged in the
battle.
They pierce the Soviets' defense lines
and trap them in huge encirclements, or
cauldrons.
On June the 28th, after just 3 days of
violent combat, Minsk falls.
A major victory for the Wehrmacht.
But the battle is far from over.
For days on end, artillery tanks and
aircraft pummel the Soviet soldiers who
are trapped in the encirclements
and soon find themselves short of
munitions and shells.
Tens of thousands of Soviet soldiers die
under German fire.
On July the 9th, the survivors have no
choice but to surrender.
Almost 300,000 soldiers are taken
prisoner.
A German soldier witnesses their
surrender.
>> A large earthy brown crocodile comes
slowly down the road towards us,
dragging its feet.
It emits a subdued hum like that of a
hive of bees.
They're Russian prisoners of war.
We cannot see the end of the column.
As they approach, we are overwhelmed by
their terrible sickening stench.
>> Hitler draws attention to the great
victory at Minsk by being filmed in a
plane flying over the destroyed city.
The message is clear.
The Red Army has just suffered a
decisive defeat.
He shares his optimism with his
generals.
The war in the East is pretty much won.
The Bolshevik Army will never recover
from these defeats.
But in Ukraine, on the southern front,
the situation is far from under control.
No lightning attacks or huge
encirclements here.
With the Soviet's stiff resistance,
every small amount of progress comes at
the expense of heavy casualties.
Hans Rohde is on the front line.
A printer in civilian life, married, and
the father of a 5-year-old girl, he's
31.
In his journal, published posthumously,
he describes his entry into Lutsk, a
town in western Ukraine.
>> The local prison is a grizzly sight.
Over 100 men,
political prisoners no doubt,
were slaughtered like cattle
by the Red Army prior to its retreat.
>> [laughter]
[cough]
>> Makes us mad.
All of a sudden a comrade flashes a few
Red Army soldiers out of their hiding
place.
He finds some Jews, too.
We give them a solo gun performance,
which echoes around the prison and
sends the scum straight to hell.
>> For the soldiers of the Wehrmacht, high
on Nazi propaganda,
the Jewish Bolshevist clique has turned
the Soviet people against Germany.
>> [music]
>> The political commissars, obviously
Jews, they're sure of it,
fanaticize the Red Army soldiers through
terror.
They've been ordered not to treat them
as of war, but to systematically shoot
them.
>> Behind the front line in the territories
occupied by the Germans the same macabre
scenario is repeated.
Assisted by the Wehrmacht the
Einsatzgruppen death squads massacre the
Jews.
Initially only the men
and encourage local militia to carry out
violent pogroms.
30,000 Jews are murdered in the first
week of the invasion alone.
A death squad commander reports to his
superiors.
>> It is quite astonishing how ill-informed
the Jews [music] are about our attitude
towards them.
>> A young girl recounts a conversation
between her father and a Jewish friend
en route to an assembly point.
>> My father advised a Jewish friend who
had been summoned by the Germans to hide
in the forest as quickly as possible.
The latter replied,
"They're sending us to Palestine."
My father retorted that wherever the
Germans have been, they have killed all
the Jews.
But our neighbor went on,
"The Germans are a people of great
culture.
They will not lie to us. It is the
Bolsheviks who lie constantly."
>> In Kiev,
the Wehrmacht is just 100 km away.
The citizens start to feel scared.
Irina Khoroshunova is a painter and
scenographer, but because of the war,
she's had to take a job as a librarian.
In her journal, published with the title
Kiev Diaries, she writes,
>> "People have gone mad.
Their faces all express the same desire
to flee,
as if there were a plague or leprosy
epidemic.
The sight of party members cramming into
their vehicles, pianos, big mirrors, and
wardrobes, on which their wives and
children are seated, only adds to the
widespread panic.
Pieces of paper flutter in the Kiev sky.
Archives are burned.
I try to remain calm in this atmosphere
of general chaos,
but I give in to fear,
and like everyone else, I'm prepared to
go anywhere, just as long as I can flee.
>> In Moscow, too, anxiety is mounting.
The Red Army suffers defeat after
defeat.
And Stalin has not spoken since the
invasion began.
Wild rumors circulate.
Has he fled?
Has he been overthrown?
The supreme leader must urgently show he
is still in control.
On the morning of July the 3rd, the news
spreads.
Stalin is to make a radio address.
In factories, rail stations, stores,
kolkhozes, and the main streets of every
town and city,
life comes to an abrupt halt as the
nation hangs onto every word blaring
from the loudspeakers.
For the first time ever, Stalin
addresses the Soviets as partners and
requests their help.
He knows that the people will not fight
for the survival of the Bolshevist
regime.
Instead, he appeals to their
nationalism.
A great patriotic war, named after
Russia's war against Napoleon, will
liberate the country from the fascist
invaders.
The country's educated urban youth is
particularly touched by this appeal.
This is so of Georgy Efron,
the 16-year-old son of the poet Marina
Tsvetaeva,
who kept a diary until his death at the
front in 1943.
The Soviet state has persecuted his
family,
and yet he feels his place is behind
Stalin.
>> Stalin said would be beaten,
just as Napoleon and Wilhelm were.
And that no army is invincible.
I believe that the war the Nazis are
waging against the USSR is the beginning
of their end.
At least we know who the enemy is.
I have always been anti-Nazi and have
always seen the Third Reich as the
enemy.
>> A young compatriot echoes these
sentiments.
>> Stalin spoke to us, addressing us as his
brothers and sisters.
And everyone suddenly forgot their
resentment.
We had an uncle who was imprisoned in a
gulag, but mother said, "First let's
defend the motherland. The rest can
wait."
>> The Great Patriotic War becomes the
focus of Stalin's propaganda.
Painters are hired to produce posters to
the glory of the Red Army.
The soldier at the front becomes the
ultimate role model, courageous, willing
to sacrifice everything for the
motherland.
But Soviet propaganda also glorifies the
soldiers of the home front, the nation's
workers.
Their efforts must be focused on one
goal, increase productivity.
More machine guns, shells, and tanks to
replace the phenomenal amount of
equipment already lost.
Comrade Stalin keeps an eye on things.
It is said he recorded all the
production figures in his little leather
notebook.
>> Late July, the tanks that have just
rolled off the production line are
deployed at the front.
They're not sophisticated like the
German tanks, but are sturdy and more
powerful.
New units are ordered to launch into
counterattacks that are poorly
coordinated and costly in terms of human
lives.
However, for the first time, the Soviets
managed to slow the German spectacular
progress.
July the 24th, Joseph Goebbels, the
Reich Propaganda Minister, writes in his
diary, "It is gradually becoming clear
that the Eastern Campaign is no stroll
to Moscow."
One month into the offensive, Operation
Barbarossa is far from the triumph
Germany had hoped for.
The Bolshevik regime has not collapsed.
The Red Army puts up unexpected
resistance. The Wehrmacht's progress is
slowed.
The specter of a prolonged war looms in
everyone's mind.
General Gotthard Heinrici commands an
infantry corps on the central front. He
writes to his wife every day.
His letters were published after the
war.
>> How much longer will this campaign last?
No one knows.
We have the impression that even if
Moscow is captured,
the war will continue somewhere else in
this endless country.
>> The troops cover 30 to 60 km a day.
The panzers lightning attacks at the
start of the offensive have left the
infantry far behind.
To catch up, they have to make a forced
march in the heat and dust.
Artilleryman Hans Roth recounts,
>> Our pace is extreme.
We barely had time to eat.
And we dare not even think about [music]
sleep.
During our rare breaks, we drag
ourselves about on our rubbery legs.
The sun beats down mercilessly on our
heads.
The dust is so thick that I cannot see
the person in front of me.
My eyes sting and burn.
This dirt gets into everything.
>> In one of his July letters, General
Heinrici expresses his alarm.
>> At each stop, my men drop to the ground
like flies
and sleep in the shade of their
vehicles,
surrounded by dust.
Water is as precious as gold.
Yesterday, I found a wagoner slumped
against his horse, sleeping on his feet
as if dead.
The extreme nervous tension comes not
only from the ever-changing situation,
but also from the danger for all
of being attacked.
>> Cut off from the protection of the
panzers and scattered in the vastness of
the Soviet Union, the small German units
fall into ambushes, especially at the
rear.
The assailants are Red Army soldiers
who've escaped the huge encirclements
and taken refuge in the forests and
marshes.
The majority attack isolated convoys
simply to get food, but a few continue
to fight.
Private Willy Peter Reese has just
joined his battalion.
An aspiring writer, the young soldier
kept a diary until his death on the
Eastern Front, which was published
posthumously as A Stranger to Myself.
>> Eight of our soldiers were sleeping in a
secluded house on the edge of the
village
when the Russians surrounded it.
Two jumped out of the window and were
shot on the spot.
Two got up, half asleep, and were killed
when the enemy entered the house.
Two others were captured.
Another was sleeping in the hayloft and
had a panic attack.
>> [snorts]
>> The remaining soldier hid behind a
sideboard.
The Russians lit matches
but did not manage to find him in the
dark.
He too descended into madness.
The following day,
one of our soldiers chucked a crate of
hand grenades at 100 Russian prisoners
and shot the survivors with a submachine
gun.
>> Constant insecurity, disorientation,
disgust, hatred, resentment, need for
vengeance.
This flammable mix is rendered explosive
by the criminal orders of March 1941
which instructed the Wehrmacht how to
behave towards civilians.
Collective reprisals are allowed.
Amnesty is guaranteed to any soldier
committing war crimes.
Orders are given to the army to work
closely with the Einsatzgruppen, the
special units at the rear that
methodically murdered the Reich's
enemies,
political opponents, resistance
fighters, and Jews.
>> [music]
>> Early August, Soviet propaganda
glorifies the model soldier, the
successes of the Red Army, and of the
Great Patriotic War.
But in the field, the troops pay a high
price for these minor victories.
Hundreds of thousands dead, countless
wounded.
The feeling of being cannon fodder for
incompetent commanders.
As a result, soldiers surrender in
droves.
For Stalin, all opposition must be
nipped in the bud. [music]
Nikolai Nikulin, who signed up for
idealistic reasons, witnesses the
crackdown during his basic training. He
recounts in his memoirs,
>> "The lads of the division were made to
line up in the square in front of the
barracks.
We were told to stand to attention as
two men without belts were brought
outside.
The captain read out a document to them.
They were sentenced to death for
desertion.
Before we even realized what was
happening, they were summarily shot
without any form of trial.
We dispersed in dead silence.
In fact, the two executed lads had
simply left without permission to visit
their families.
But they were publicly shot in order to
reinforce discipline.
It was horrifyingly simple.
>> During the summer of 1941, terror
infiltrates every echelon.
The political commissars at the front
are encouraged to report any officer or
soldier with a suspicious attitude.
Detachments of soldiers are deployed
behind the fighting troops
to shoot anyone who retreats.
A new decree, order number 270,
introduces a particularly cruel form of
blackmail.
Any soldier who is captured will be
considered a traitor, and their family
will be subjected to automatic arrest.
The soldiers have no choice but to fight
to the death.
Behind the lines, too, in Moscow,
Leningrad, and Kiev, hordes of spies
from the NKVD, the secret police,
are on the lookout for saboteurs in the
rear,
panic-mongers, defeatists,
in a word, the enemy within.
The slightest criticism can lead to the
gulag.
>> In her library in Kiev,
Irina Karachunova can feel Stalin's iron
grip tightening.
She's all the more worried because
during the purge of 1937,
her mother was executed after being
denounced.
>> Arrests are increasing.
People see spies, saboteurs, and
traitors everywhere.
Adults and even children take all those
they consider suspicious to the NKVD's
offices.
Being very well dressed is suspicious.
Being badly dressed is equally so.
I know that this has already led to
terrible mistakes.
Are any of those arrested genuinely
guilty?
It's hard to say.
>> Suspicion spreads.
Self-censorship increases.
The only modes of expression possible
are rumors, diaries, and solitary anger.
Young Nikolai Nikolin's war diaries are
peppered with cries of anger.
>> An order is given.
A hill must be taken.
The regiment launches an attack and
continues the offensive for weeks with
huge daily losses.
"This massacre must end," cries an
officer.
"They have a concrete fortress, and all
we have is a pathetic little cannon.
Instantly, a snitch. There are plenty in
each section. Reports to the political
instructor.
He questioned our victory in the
presence of our soldiers.
His name is immediately written on a
document that has already been filled
in.
And the culprit is either shot or sent
to a small disciplinary battalion.
Which amounts to the same thing.
>> [music]
>> Mid-August, Hitler is filmed visiting
the headquarters of Army Group Center.
Operation Barbarossa is marking time.
With German forces attacking along three
axes, it is impossible to deal the
decisive blow.
The generals think they should converge
on Moscow, the nerve center of the
communist regime.
But aware this [music] is where the
Soviets have concentrated the bulk of
their troops,
Hitler intends to take them by surprise
and attack where they least expect it.
In the south, east of Kiev.
By encircling the Soviet forces,
on August the 25th, Army Group Center's
panzers sweep towards Kiev.
The same day, the tanks of the Army
Group South race to meet them through a
sea of ripe wheat.
Hitler is a step closer to his goal of
expanding the Reich eastwards to gain
Lebensraum, or living space, which he
believes the Germans are entitled to.
It is inconceivable that a higher people
should painfully exist on a soil too
narrow for it.
While amorphous masses, which contribute
nothing to civilization,
occupy infinite tracts of a soil that is
one of the richest in the world.
In 20 [music] years time, Europeans in
search of a better life will no longer
emigrate to America,
but will settle [music] in this new
Eldorado in the East.
On the outskirts of Kyiv, Hans Rohde
discovers the cost of these dreams of
conquest.
Mutilated bodies, ruins,
blown-out vehicles,
everything around him is gradually
destroyed.
>> It's insane.
I'm under fire.
I'm looking at a tree,
sunlight, and the rays filtering through
its branches.
How I yearn for the town's forest, where
I used to stroll on Sundays with Rosl.
A few large shells fall.
Where's my tree?
A cloud of ominous black smoke has
engulfed it.
As the smoke rises, the tree starts to
lean, slowly at first, then faster and
faster until it crashes to the ground.
In this nightmare, there's no place for
my forest dreams.
>> On September the 16th, General Heinz
Guderian of Army Group Center is filmed
for the German news when his army links
up with [music] Army Group South just
outside Kiev.
Hitler's strategy has worked.
For the Red Army, it's a massive
disaster. [music]
The worst since the invasion began.
30,000 vehicles, 650,000 soldiers, 13
generals fall into the Germans' hands.
September the 19th,
German forces enter Kiev without
resistance.
The Red Army left the city 2 days prior
after planting time-delayed mines in
many government buildings, which explode
as the troops go by.
For 5 days, the city is a blazing
inferno,
causing the death of hundreds of
soldiers.
The Germans immediately blame the city's
Jewish population for these attacks.
On September the 29th, General
Eberhardt, the new governor, orders all
members of the community to gather by
the Jewish cemetery,
supposedly to await transfer.
Everyone must bring their most valuable
possessions.
In her diaries, Irina Khoroshunova
recounts her encounter with the grim
procession.
>> They are escorted by serried ranks of
soldiers.
Until now, all the columns of prisoners
I have seen were flanked by a few armed
guards at most, but this is different.
The Germans strictly forbid anyone to
approach this group of prisoners.
By a house, one of the men looks up and
dares to ask for water from a woman at
her window.
He walks towards her, then quickens his
step.
Two shots ring out.
He is killed instantly.
They're Jews.
>> The prisoners are taken by German
soldiers and Ukrainian auxiliary police
officers to the Babi Yar gorge near
Kyiv.
Hans Roth is occupying the city with his
unit.
He meets a comrade from his village who
is a member of the death squad and takes
him to the site of the massacre.
Even he, who regards the Jews as enemies
of the Reich,
is appalled by what he sees.
>> I'll never ever forget this horrific
sight.
There are Jews standing on the edge of
the gorge. The machine guns are whipping
into them.
They fall over the edge 50 m.
Whatever stays at the edge is swept
over.
When the quota of 1,000 is filled,
the pile of corpses is blown up and
covered with earth.
"Isn't the detonation a great idea?"
says the fresh-faced blond youth.
My god, the boy is 19 years old.
19.
Without saying a word, I turn and
practically run back to town.
>> In the space of 2 days, September the
29th and 30th,
33,771
Jews are executed by members of the
Waffen SS
>> [music]
>> and the Einsatzgruppen
with the help of Wehrmacht soldiers and
Ukrainian auxiliary police.
Men, women,
children.
Babi Yar is a turning point in the
radicalization of the Nazi extermination
policy.
This is not the first massacre of women
and children,
but the Germans have never murdered so
many Jews in such a short time.
Over 1 and 1/2 million Soviet Jews will
be exterminated in mass shootings in the
Holocaust by bullets.
The genocide plan will later to
to the rest of Europe and rationalized,
industrialized
in the death camps.
Young Irena can do nothing but utter her
despair.
>> I write and I'm horrified by my own
words.
I write, but my words express nothing.
I write because the world has to know
that a terrible crime is being committed
and it must be avenged.
I write and at the same time the mass
murder continues of innocent and
defenseless children, women, and old
people, many of whom are buried alive
because the Germans are thrifty and do
not like to waste bullets unnecessarily.
And we are utterly powerless.
>> Following the capture of Kiev, Operation
Barbarossa resumes.
Nothing now stands in the way of the
conquest of Moscow
before winter.
>> Mhm.